Okay, boker tov בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is
lamed chet ל"ח lamed chet 32. We pick up in lamed aleph
ל"א, lamed aleph, we are behind, the very top of lamed aleph
ל"א lamed aleph amud bet עמוד ב. amud bet.
I'm next to you, you're ahead. So you see what happens?
Your presence keeps us ahead. So we had just taught a new
mishna משנה mishna about the difference between other korbanot קרבנות korbanot that
have a mum מום mum and bechor בכור bechor and ma'aser מעשר,
ma'aser, that other korbanot קרבנות korbanot because you have to redeem them,
you estimate their value, and so you have to determine how much
will they sell in the marketplace for. So we allow you after
you redeem them actually to sell them in the marketplace so that
you will value them, their market value will be higher, you'll be
able to sell them retail not wholesale, and opposed to bechor בכור
bechor and ma'aser מעשר ma'aser which you do not redeem.
So let's take a look at the Gemara גמרא Gemara top of
lamed aleph ל"א lamed aleph amud bet עמוד ב. amud bet. Kol
pesulei hamukdashin hanas'am lehekdesh כל פסולי המוקדשין הנאתן להקדש. kol pesulei hamukdashin
hanas'am lehekdesh.
All invalid korbanot קרבנות, korbanot, hekdesh הקדש hekdesh ultimately benefits once they
are redeemed because it gets transferred to money based on their value
and that money gets used to buy another korban קרבן. korban. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, emat אימת, emat, one minute, when is
hekdesh הקדש hekdesh going to benefit? Ileima le'achar pidyono אילימא לאחר פדיונו,
ileima le'achar pidyono, if you say after you redeem it, that then
hekdesh הקדש hekdesh gets its value after it's redeemed, then hanas'am lehekdesh
הנאתן להקדש, hanas'am lehekdesh, so what do you mean hanas'am lehekdesh הנאתן
להקדש? hanas'am lehekdesh? Hanas'am leba'alim הנאתן לבעלים. hanas'am leba'alim. After it's redeemed,
the owners benefit from the animal, not hekdesh הקדש. hekdesh. So when
does hekdesh הקדש hekdesh get the value? Ela lav אלא לאו, ela
lav, ela lifnei
pidyonam אלא לפני פדיונם. ela lifnei pidyonam. Before they're redeemed. Before they're
redeemed, they're owned by hekdesh הקדש, hekdesh, and then it says any
benefit that will come from them will ultimately go to hekdesh הקדש,
hekdesh, right? Once they're redeemed, the benefit's already gone, has already been
transferred. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, okay, but before
them, how could you say nishchatin נשחטין, nishchatin, how could you say
you slaughter it in the marketplace to raise its value? Ha ba'ei
ha'amadah veha'arachah הא בעי העמדה והערכה. ha ba'ei ha'amadah veha'arachah. You can't
slaughter it once it's hekdesh הקדש. hekdesh. If it's slaughtered while it's
still hekdesh הקדש, hekdesh, you won't be able to redeem it because
then once it's dead, you can't redeem a hekdesh הקדש hekdesh animal
if it's dead. Ha nicha leman de'amar kodshei mizbe'ach lo hayu bichlal
ha'amadah veha'arachah הניחא למאן דאמר קדשי מזבח לא היו בכלל העמדה והערכה.
ha nicha leman de'amar kodshei mizbe'ach lo hayu bichlal ha'amadah veha'arachah. It
would work according to the one that says that things that were
sanctified for the altar do not need to be stood up, they
don't need to be alive when they're redeemed. So then you could
say yishachet ישחט yishachet and then you redeem it. Ela leman de'amar
hayu bichlal ha'amadah veha'arachah אלא למאן דאמר היו בכלל העמדה והערכה. ela
leman de'amar hayu bichlal ha'amadah veha'arachah. But according to the opinion that
korbanot קרבנות korbanot even with a blemish can only be redeemed when
they're alive, you can't say yishachet ישחט yishachet and then you redeem
it, you have to redeem it first. So mai ika lemeimar מאי
איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, what can you say? So there's really
no real problem here in this mishna משנה. mishna. It's just the
Gemara's גמרא Gemara trying to figure out the phrasing. We all know
the sense. The sense of the mishna משנה mishna is hekdesh הקדש
hekdesh is going to benefit after it's from the amount of its
redemption, and therefore you're allowed to shachet שחט shachet it in the
marketplace to raise its retail value. The problem is just how do
you understand the timing? Hekdesh הקדש hekdesh is going to benefit at
the moment of redemption. To say you're therefore allowed to shachet שחט,
shachet, but that's happening after the redemption. So how do you just
read that? And the Gemara גמרא Gemara just sort of reads says
the following, yeah, you read those together. Here's how you read it.
You read it sort of as sort of backwards looking or forward
looking. Here's what you read it. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says,
ela lav le'achar pidyonam אלא לאו לאחר פדיונם. ela lav le'achar pidyonam.
You're right. Hekdesh הקדש hekdesh will hekdesh הקדש hekdesh the shachting happens
after you redeem it. Umai hanas'am lehekdesh ומאי הנאתן להקדש, umai hanas'am
lehekdesh,
so you're going to shachet שחט shachet it after you redeem it.
What does it mean hekdesh הקדש hekdesh benefits? Not hekdesh הקדש hekdesh
benefits at this moment that you're shachting it. What it means is
ademeikara אדמעיקרא, ademeikara, it means originally when you redeemed it, hekdesh הקדש
hekdesh was going to benefit from that act of redemption, and therefore
now you're allowed later you're allowed to shachet שחט shachet it in
the marketplace in order so the way it was estimated earlier when
you redeemed it would have been at a higher value based on
its higher retail value. Is that clear? Meaning here I'm trying to
value it, the retail value I'm going to give this, the market
value is going to be based on what I'm able to do
after I redeem it. Okay, so that's what it means. Decheivan desharei
lehu limaker be'itliz venishchat be'itliz דכיון דשרי להו למכר באטליז ונשחט באטליז,
decheivan desharei lehu limaker be'itliz venishchat be'itliz, since we allow you to
shachet שחט shachet it in the marketplace and sell it in the
marketplace and all those things will raise its retail value, venishkalin belitra
ונשקלין בליטרא, venishkalin belitra, to sell it based on to weigh it
out pound by pound to sell it, so tafi ufarek meikara טפי
ופרק מעיקרא, tafi ufarek meikara, you'll raise the value when you originally
redeem it. So all it's basically just saying is the mishna's משנה
mishna referred to two points of time. There's the point of time
of redemption, which is you determine its value, that's where hekdesh הקדש
hekdesh benefits, but the way you determine its value is based on
what is going to be how you're going to be able to
sell it afterwards. So therefore we let you sell it afterwards in
the marketplace to raise its value so that earlier when you redeemed
it, you estimated it at a higher value. Okay. Chutz min habechor
umin hama'aser shenas'am leba'alim חוץ מן הבכור ומן המעשר שהנאתן לבעלים. chutz
min habechor umin hama'aser shenas'am leba'alim.
But when it comes to bechor בכור bechor and ma'aser מעשר, ma'aser,
you do not redeem it, you eat it, you the kohen כהן
kohen or you the owner if it's a ma'aser מעשר ma'aser eat
it, and therefore we do not let you sell it retail, which
is not respectful for it because there's no point of raising its
market value,
and therefore you have to sell it like privately and you don't
weigh it out. If you want to sell it, otherwise you will
eat it. But there הקדש hekdesh won't benefit, you're just, it's not
going to be redeemed. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this: בשלמא Bishlama בכור, bechor,
so I understand the case of בכור. bechor. באטליז הוא דלא מזדבן,
Be'itlis hu delo mizdaben,
it's not sold in the meat marketplace. הא בבית מזדבן, Ha bevayis
mizdaben, it could be sold out of your house.
So אלא ella that's fine. Nobody ever said you can't sell a
בכור. bechor. Again, just to clarify, right, a בכור bechor is not
like תרומה. truma. A בכור בעל מום, bechor ba'al mum, right, that's
what we're talking about, it's שחט shechted outside the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. It's owned by the כהן, kohen, but it doesn't have the,
it doesn't have a קדושה kedusha that limits who can eat it,
who can eat it. So therefore he could sell it to another
כהן, kohen, he could sell it to a ישראל, Yisrael, whoever he
wants, okay, as long as they just go ahead and eat it,
which is what you're supposed to do with a בכור בעל מום.
bechor ba'al mum. That's fine.
אלא Ella מעשר, ma'aser, but it also says implies that the same
is true by מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. בבית Bevayis it sounds like
I can't sell in the marketplace, but I can sell out of
my home. One minute, מי מזדבן? mi mizdaben? Since when can you
sell מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, even with a blemish? Why not? Why
the difference? Because of the פסוק. pasuk. דתנו De'atnu תנא tana ברייתא,
braisa, בכור נאמר, bechor ne'emar, by בכור bechor it says לא תפדה.
lo tipadeh.
It says that you shall not redeem it. It says by the
בכור, bechor, אך בכור שור או בכור עז לא תפדה קדש הם.
ach bechor shor o bechor ez lo tipadeh kodesh heim. They shall
not be redeemed, they are holy. Okay so fine, you don't redeem
it, you just eat it with its blemish. That's what we've been
talking about. ונמכר חי, Venimkar chai, and you can but you can
sell it even if it's alive once it has a blemish. The
only restriction on a בכור bechor is well you can't use it,
you can't shear it, you can't redeem it, but the תורה Torah
never says don't sell it once it has a blemish. ובמעשר נאמר,
Uma'aser ne'emar, however by מעשר ma'aser it says לא יגאל. lo yiga'el.
It says, you know, והיה תמורתו יהיה קדש לא יגאל. vehaya temurato
yihiyeh kodesh lo yiga'el. It at
its exchange should be קודש, kodesh, if you try to do a
תמורה tmura with מעשר ma'aser which you're not allowed, it shall not
be redeemed. Now redeemed normally means the same as תפדה, tipadeh, which
is to redeem it on money. So why does that mean that
you can't sell מעשר? ma'aser? It just says don't redeem it. So
let's take a look. ואינו נמכר, Ve'eino nimkar, cannot be sold, לא
חי lo chai neither alive, ולא שחוט velo shachut or
even after it's been slaughtered, לא תם lo tam
certainly not without a blemish, certainly not unblemished because then you have
to bring it as a קרבן, korban, ולא בעל מום velo ba'al
mum not even if it has a blemish, even if you're allowed
to eat it you can't sell מעשר. ma'aser. So first we have
to understand, געזונטהייט gezuntheit to everybody, first we have to understand why,
where do you get that from the verse? Why it shouldn't be
sold? And then once we figure that out, we have to explain
our משנה mishna which implies it can be sold, or you know
pretty strongly implies it can be sold. So let's take a look.
So first track we're going to skip over the first part and
we'll get to that later, but I'll just tell you now לא
יגאל lo yiga'el is linked to a פסוק, pasuk, another פסוק, pasuk,
yeah go ahead.
So I was thinking about the לא יגאל lo yiga'el from like
when you sell your house.
Okay Michael, you can really write the גמרא. Gemara. So yes, it
says by maybe he did,
actually there is a לא יגאל lo yiga'el by בתי ערי חומה,
batei arei chomah, there's also לא יגאל lo yiga'el by חרם, cherem,
and those types of things cannot be redeemed, they cannot be sold.
So actually it was close but it was actually more by the
one by חרם, cherem, but regardless there's a לא יגאל lo yiga'el
that's linked to a לא ימכר. lo yimacher. That's we're going to
get to that later. Okay, but right now the question is you
can't sell מעשר, ma'aser, how does it come up at all? How
come our משנה mishna implies just don't sell it in the marketplace?
So let's take a look. דהא הוה איקשי ליה
לרב ששת, Dehah hiyeha itchelei leh leRav Sheshes, באורתא be'orta Rav Sheshes
was very bothered with this at night. You see, this is what
keeps, this is what keeps a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham up at
night, right? Trying to figure out פשט pshat in this משנה. mishna.
Okay.
ומשניא בקדמותא, Veshanya bekadmusah, and he and he answered it when he
woke up early in the morning, right, he slept on it and
the answer came to him בברייתא, bibraisa, he used a ברייתא braisa
to answer this. What was it, במעשר בהמה bema'aser behemah and we'll
see what the ברייתא braisa is in a minute, but here we're
going to go to the bottom line, here's the answer. במעשר בהמה
של יתומים עסקינן, Bema'aser behemah sheshel yesomim maskinan, we're talking about מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behemah that's owned by יתומים, yesomim, which is basically you
know assumed to generally be people who can't who you know have
very limited funds and we're very concerned about their ability to support
themselves. They don't have anybody any breadwinner or whatever presumably young יתומים.
yesomim. ומשום השבת אבידה נהגו
בה. Umishum hashavas aveidah nahagu bah. And the concern is returning a
lost object. It means that figuratively. It means if you שחט shecht
this huge cow, okay or sheep or whatever it is and you
don't let me sell it, a lot of the meat is going
to go to waste. And if I maybe if you know maybe
if I'm an adult or whatever, first of all I can be
more controlling the situation and salt it, maybe I can invite people
over and then next time they'll you know they'll return the favor
they'll invite me over, but anyway if it's יתומים yesomim and you
don't let let it be sold it's going to there's going to
be a tremendous amount of money that's going to go to waste,
so we'd let them sell it. Now of course well that's all
very nice that you're concerned about יתומים, yesomim, but if it's a
biblical prohibition, how do you let them sell? So what we are
going to see later in the גמרא Gemara is, is that the
גמרא's Gemara going to understand that the actual biblical prohibition is only
when the animal is alive. That after it's שחט shechted it actually
is going to be permissible to sell it biblically, only rabbinically restricted
and therefore for יתומים yesomim we waive that and because we did
not
It's only,
it's only if there's too much for them to eat.
Yeah, I mean that would be in that assumed context, okay?
So you sell, you sell, in other words they could derive benefit
financially from having sold the animal
as well as
the meat itself.
If they שחט shecht this מעשר, maaser, they can only eat 10
pounds before it goes bad, so they let people know that they
have some lamb meat to sell and people show up to their
house and they buy it in a private way, you don't go
to the market. And said right, and no, no, no, not you
sell it so that it goes to orphans. If there are orphans
that have this animal, then they are allowed to sell it so
that they don't lose their money, okay? If you have this type
of an animal, then we figure look, even if you do suffer
a loss, you know, you can provide for yourself anyway.
But if they're orphans, they're young children, what do they know about
selling animals? Can I ask a stupid question?
No, it's not a stupid question. So you're right, so presumably there's
somebody that's helping arrange their affairs, okay? So therefore, you're right, but
that person, you know, even if you are the appointed guardian of
these orphans, financial sort of guardian of these orphans, right, you know,
we're still are concerned for their welfare more than we are with
people with a parent. So therefore we let you, yes, sell it
to and put the money away for their benefit. But you can't
sell if it you can't just sell oh I'll sell it and
then I'll give the money to צדקה. tzedakah. We're not talking about
that. We're talking about the orphans themselves are the ones with the
animal, okay? All right. So, that so that's why, but of course
that will only work if it's a rabbinic restriction, so we will
explain later that it is only a rabbinic restriction after it's been
שחט. shechted. So now the גמרא Gemara says, רב אידי סרסיא דרב
ששת הוה. Rav Idi sarsia d'Rav Sheshet hava. Now רב אידי Rav
Idi was רב ששת Rav Sheshet who was bothered by this at
night and woke up the next morning. Now רב אידי Rav Idi
was his שמש, shamash, he's like, you know, I keep on telling
people that that's an open position I have here. Yeah.
So anyway, so רב אידי Rav Idi was his attendant of רב
ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב אידי סרסיא שמשי. Rav Idi sarsia shamshay.
I know, I'm not sure, might be a little bit more like
attendant and maybe a little I'm not sure, me-o-work, I'm not sure.
שמע מיניה, Shama minei, so he heard him what?
I don't think either one. I don't think either one.
He heard so he heard from him this answer. Now you could
imagine the scene, right? He wakes up in the morning, maybe רב
אידי Rav Idi is sort of handing him his clothes, helping him
get dressed. I got the פשט! pshat! Okay, so he heard from
him this before presumably he had a chance to announce it, right,
because he was wondering thinking about it the whole night before a
chance that he had to teach it in a larger forum. אזל
אמרה בבי מדרשא. Azal amar be-bei midrasha.
So רב אידי Rav Idi went and he told the בית מדרש,
Beit Midrash, hey guys, I got good פשט! pshat! Okay, ולא אמרה
משמיה velo amar mishmei and he didn't say that רב ששת Rav
Sheshet told it to him. He just sort of said it implying
that it was him that it was his חידוש. chiddush. So שמע
רב ששת, shama Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet heard, איקפד, ikpad,
he got very upset. אמר, Amar, מאן דעקיץ, man d'akitz, the person
who sort of stung me, לכתיה עקרבא, l'aktei akrava, a scorpion should
sting him. So he felt very very he felt very personally hurt
by this and you know uttered this imprecation. Okay, we assume Bobby
he didn't mean it literally. Now the גמרא Gemara says, ורב ששת
מאי נפקא ליה מינה? ve-Rav Sheshet mai nafka lei minei? What does
רב ששת Rav Sheshet care? It's Torah! Every people learn Torah, why
should he be so concerned that it be attributed to him? Which
is funny, it's like the flip side of כל האומר דבר בשם
אומרו מביא גאולה לעולם, kol ha-omer davar beshem omro meivi geulah l'olam,
but maybe that's talking about you who's transmitting it you should give
credit, that's your moral responsibility, but from the person who actually came
up with the חידוש, chiddush, if you're really selfless and you're really
doing it לשם שמים, l'shem shamayim, why why why do you care
that it's attributed to you? So the גמרא Gemara says, דאמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, because רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says in the name of רב, Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv,
what's meant by the verse, אגורה באהלך עולמים? agura be-ohalcha olamim? דוד
David says I I will live God in your tents for worlds
forever, but worlds is plural. וכי אפשר לאדם לגור בשני עולמים? ve-chi
efshar l'adam lagur bishnei olamim? Can you live in two worlds? Presumably
this world and the next world? If you're living in this world,
you're not living in the next world, and vice versa. How could
you be living in God's tents in worlds at the same time?
אלא, Ela, and of course tent is always seen as referencing the
tent of Torah. So this is going to lead to the following
interpretation. אלא, Ela, אמר דוד, amar David, דוד David said, רבונו של
עולם, Ribono shel Olam, Master of the Universe, יאמרו דבר שמועה מפי
בעולם הזה, yomru davar shemuah mipi ba-olam hazeh, I pray that people
should tell over Torah teaching in my name in this world, and
therefore I'll live in your tents in worlds. How is that possible?
דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in the name
of רבי שמעון בן יוחי, Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, כל תלמיד חכם
שאומרים דבר שמועה מפיו בעולם הזה, kol talmid chacham she-omrim davar shemuah
mipi ba-olam hazeh, any תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that they tell over
Torah in his name in this world even after he's passed away
but people are still repeating his Torah even though he's passed away,
דובבות שפתותיו דובבות בקבר, dovvot siftotav dovvot bakever, his lips are still
mutter in the grave. So it gives life to him, it's like
he's still teaching and it gives life isn't it beautiful? His lips
are still moving in the grave if you're telling over his Torah
in this world. So therefore דוד David says if they'll tell over
my Torah after I die, then I will continue to live in
your tents in worlds. the same time. I'll be living it in
עולם הבא Olam Haba and I'll be living in it in this
world as people continue to tell over my תורה Torah and it'll
be like I'll still be learning. ואמר רב יצחק בן ביריא מאי
קרא, V'amar Rav Yitzchak ben Birya mai kra, where's the verse? וחכך
כיין הטוב, V'chichech k'yayin hatov, your cheek, your palate is like the
good wine, הולך לדודי למישרים, holech l'dodi l'meisharim, goes to my beloved
like straight away. So what does that mean? דובב שפתי ישנים, Doveiv
siftei yesheinim, the flowing from the and the שפתי ישנים, siftei yesheinim,
the ancient lips. So what does that mean? We explain it like
this. כומר של ענבים, Komer shel anavim, it's like a bunch,
a heaping, a pile of
grapes. מה כומר של ענבים, mah komer shel anavim, the same way
this bunch of grapes, כיון דאדם נוגע בו, keivan d'adam nogeia bo,
as soon as you touch it, the juices run out, דובב, doveiv,
the juices flow out. אף תלמידי חכמים, Af talmidei chachamim, so even
Torah sages, כיון שאדם אומר דבר שמועה מפיו, keivan she'adam omeir d'var
shmuah mipiv, as somebody tells over a Torah teaching in their name,
דובבות שפתותיו בקבר, dovivot siftotav bakever, their lips will mutter in the
grave. So they tie it into the פסוק, pasuk, וחכך, v'chichech, your
palate, like your mouth, is like this good wine and therefore the
same way the wine, you just touch it, the grape, and the
good grapes, the juices run out, so therefore the Torah as well,
once it's mentioned, sort of it touches the soul of that person
if you would, or connects to that person, then it continues to
flow and the lips continue to mutter. So he wanted to continue
to live in this world. He wanted to have his lips murmuring
in the grave, so he's very offended that his תורה, Torah, which
this might have been his legacy as people would have remembered this
פשט pshat to this משנה mishnah and they would have told this
over even after he died, he wanted to make sure it was
told over in his name, which of course brings up the famous
comment of Woody Allen which
is, I don't want to be made immortal by my work, I
want to be made immortal by not dying.
But since the second option is usually not available, so you can
become immortal through your work, immortal through your teaching.
If only
he feels that his lips will only move if people mention him
by name? Or is it that you just say the same...
Oh, that's an interesting point.
So you've got רב
שמעון
Rav
Shimon
knows who gets the credit. That's an interesting point. Somehow the metaphysics
of that has to be like remembering him specifically. That's a good
point.
Maybe he's in the picture here in the story.
Well, there you go and here we've got remembered because of this
story. But by the way, the phrasing is אומר דבר שמועה מפיו,
omeir d'var shmuah mipiv, not אומר דבר שמועה שלו. omeir d'var shmuah
shelo. So they say a teaching
מפיו mipiv from his mouth, something that he had taught, or they
say it like מפיו mipiv connecting to his
saying, connecting to the fact that he had taught it. But yes,
clearly that's how the גמרא Gemara is reading it.
I think they're exactly reading it like that, that they say something
over in his
name. דבר שמועה מפיו, d'var shmuah mipiv, not a שמועה shmuah that
came from his mouth, but they say it over in his name.
But it still raises the question, why was that necessary? Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, so then anyway, now we got פשט.
pshat. Now back to, that was a lovely little אגדתא Aggadata digression,
now back to the hard work. So let's take a look. It
says like this, מאי ברייתא? Mai braisa? What was the ברייתא braisa
that you got this idea that it makes a difference for
orphans? דתני, D'tani, we learned in the ברייתא, braisa, מעשר בהמה של
יתומים מוכרין אותו, ma'aser beheimah shel yetomim mochrin oso, that the מעשר
בהמה ma'aser beheimah of orphans you can sell
it. ומעשר בהמה ששחטו מבליעו בעורו ובחלבו ובגידו ובקרניו. Uma'aser beheimah sheshachto
mavlio be'oro uv'chelvo uv'gido uv'karnav. And if you שחט shacht מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser beheimah, presumably even if you're not an orphan and now you
want to sell it, here's another trick that you can sell it
if you're not an orphan. The way you could do it is
you absorb its cost in the skin and the fat and the
sinews and the horns. So you basically say, I have such a
deal for you, I will sell you the fat and the sinews
and the horns of this cow
for just ten thousand dollars, but you know what? I'll throw in
the meat for free.
So if you do that, that also is a way where you
can sell מעשר בהמה ma'aser beheimah without actually selling it. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Why are there so many attorneys that are Jews? It's just...
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Why are there so
many?
Because you see, maybe
they want to encourage that? I'm not sure. But even if you're
שדי ביה מומא, shadi bei muma, what are you going to do
with all this meat? It's not about getting around the מום, mum,
it's dealing with it after the מום. mum. So מאי קאמר, mai
ka'amar, how do you read this? What are these two things, orphans
and then this other thing? אמר אביי הכי קאמר, Amar Abayei hachi
ka'amar, this is what it means. מעשר בהמה של יתומים מוכרין אותו
בהבלעה. Ma'aser beheimah shel yetomim mochrin oso b'havla'ah. אביי Abayei reads the
two phrases together. When you are going to sell the מעשר בהמה
ma'aser beheimah of orphans, you have to do it in this way
of absorbing it, selling it sort of under the guise of something
else. מכלל, Michlal, and that would imply, according to אביי, Abayei, דגדול
בהבלעה לא, d'gadol b'havla'ah lo, that an adult... that a normal adult
cannot sell it in this sort of hidden way, absorbed way. So
מאי שנא מהא דתנן, mai shna me-ha d'tnan, how is it different
from what we taught in the משנה, mishna, הלוקח לולב מחבירו בשביעית?
halokeach lulav me-chavero b'shvi'is? If you're purchasing a לולב lulav on שביעית,
shvi'is, so in the שביעית shvi'is year itself, the לולב lulav is
from the sixth year but the אתרוג esrog is from the seventh
year. So how do you buy the אתרוג esrog if you're not
allowed to purchase, well, you might be allowed in some circumstances to
purchase stuff from שביעית shvi'is if they were harvested correctly, but we're
also afraid that the person who is selling it will not treat
the money with קדושת שביעית kedushat shvi'is and will misuse it. So
how do you get around שביעית, shvi'is, any שביעית shvi'is concerns if
you're buying the אתרוג esrog on שביעית? shvi'is? Here's what you do.
נותן לו אתרוג במתנה, noten lo esrog b'matanah, you give him the
אתרוג esrog as a gift. Just pay for the לולב, lulav, the
אתרוג esrog is a gift. לפי שאינו רשאי לוקחו בשביעית, lefi she-eino
rashai lokcho b'shvi'is, because you're not allowed to purchase it on שביעית.
shvi'is. ואתינן בה, va-atinan bah, לא רצה ליתן לו במתנה מאי? lo
ratza liten lo b'matanah mai? And we ask, let's say the storekeeper
doesn't want to give it to you as a gift. So ואמר
רב יהודה, v'amar Rav Yehuda, fine, מבליע לו דמי אתרוג בלולב. mavli'a
lo d'mei esrog b'lulav. You absorb, you swallow up the cost of
the אתרוג esrog in the לולב. lulav. The לולב lulav now doesn't
cost ten dollars, it costs fifty dollars, and the אתרוג esrog is
a free gift. Of course, if you buy the fifty dollar לולב
lulav you get one type of אתרוג esrog gift, and if you
buy the hundred dollar לולב lulav you get another type of אתרוג
esrog gift. But anyway, the אתרוג esrog is a gift and the
cost is in the לולב. lulav. So if we're allowed to do
it there, why aren't, why are you saying that you're only allowed
by orphans to do it? Why shouldn't even normal people be allowed
to do that? So the גמרא Gemara says, התם לא מוכחא מילתא.
hatam lo mukcha milta. There it's not so obvious. You know, you
pay a lot of money for the לולב, lulav, the הדסים, hadasim,
and the ערבות, aravos, to make that a little bit higher for
the cost and absorb the cost of the אתרוג esrog is not
so blatantly obvious that you're tricking. הכא מוכחא מילתא. hacha mukcha milta.
Here it's very obvious. Right? How much do the horns and the
sinews of a cow cost as opposed to how much the meat
costs? So charging ten thousand dollars for the horns and the sinews
is clearly a blatantly, you know, a farce, and therefore it is
problematic and we only allow it for the orphans. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, אם כן, im ken, if that פשט pshat
in the ברייתא braita that it's only being allowed for the orphans,
מעשר בהמה תרי זימני למה לי? ma'aser behemah trei zimni lama li?
Why did it have to say מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah of orphans,
here's what you do, מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah you can sell בהבלעה.
b'havla'ah. It sort of just,
the fact that it started the sentence again with מעשר בהמה ma'aser
behemah seems like it's talking about a second case. אלא אמר רבא,
ela amar Rava, rather says רבא, Rava, הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, here's
how you read it. מעשר בהמה של יתומים מוכרין אותו כדרכו. ma'aser
behemah shel yetomim mochrin oto k'darko. When it comes to the מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behemah of orphans, you can sell it normally, we don't
have to do any tricks. ומעשר בהמה דגדול, u-ma'aser behemah d'gadol, and
if it's the מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah of a
normal adult, ששחטו, she-shachato, מבליעו בעורו ובחלבו ובגידו ובקרניו. mavli'o b'oro u-v'chelvo
u-v'gido u-v'karnav. Then you can do this trick of selling the cost,
absorbing it into the cost of the other parts of the animal.
Now according to אביי, Abaye, you never technically sold the מעשר ma'aser
because you always absorbed the cost even in the case of the
orphans, and therefore fine, you could say it's biblically prohibited but you
did a little work around, a trick, which we'll allow you for
orphans. But according to רבא, Rava, orphans they sold it straight away
without any tricks. How can you sell it? What about the biblical
prohibition? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, מנא אמינא לה, mna amina lah, where do I know this
that you can actually, it is possible to allow it straight away?
דכתיב, d'chtiv, because the verse says, והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קודש. v'hayah
hu u-tmurato yihyeh kodesh. It says by מעשר, ma'aser, if you exchanged
it, which you're not allowed, that it and its תמורה, tmura, its
exchange, are sanctified. לא יגאל, lo yiga'el, it shall not be redeemed.
And that word לא יגאל lo yiga'el we're going to learn means
it also cannot be sold. אימת, eimat, now let's understand the context
of this verse. אימת עושה תמורה? eimat oseh tmura? When do you
do this act of תמורה, tmura, exchanging that the קדושה kedusha transfers,
which again you're not allowed but if it's so it's effective? When
do you do it? מחיים. me-chayim. That's only if the animal's alive.
Once the animal's dead, תמורה tmura doesn't work. תמורה tmura only works
for קרבנות korbanos when they are alive. So therefore if the פסוק
pasuk about the תמורה tmura is in the context when it's alive,
אימת אינו ניגאל, eimat eino niga'al, when is the restriction on selling
it, which also means it can't be sold? So when is the
restriction on selling it? Also מחיים. me-chayim. Also only when it's alive.
הא לאחר שחיטה, ha le-achar shechita, once you've slaughtered it and it's
no longer a מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, it's just meat, it's been
slaughtered, then ניגאל, niga'al, it can be ניגאל, niga'al, which here is
being interpreted to mean it can be sold. So based on the
context of the verse, we're going to say yes, you're not allowed
to sell it but only when it's alive. After you שחט shacht
it, you can. And that's going to give us the opportunity to
be lenient by orphans. So לרבנן, l'rabanan, הוא דגזרו לאחר שחיטה. hu
d'gazru le-achar shechita. It's only the Rabbis that prohibited you to sell
it even after it was slaughtered. אטו לפני שחיטה, atu lifnei shechita,
that it will lead to before slaughter. So דבר הנישום מחיים גזרו
רבנן לאחר שחיטה אטו לפני שחיטה. davar ha-nishom me-chayim gazru rabanan le-achar
shechita atu lifnei shechita. So first point number one is the Rabbis
only made their restriction regarding meat. Only something that goes into factoring
out its cost while it's alive is what they restricted you to
sell when it's dead. Meaning only the part that's really saleable in
a normal market is what you're not allowed to sell, which is
the meat. They never said you weren't allowed to sell like the
horns or the bones or whatever. That's why number one you can
sell those horns and bones and do the trick of, you know,
of selling the meat as a gift. So דבר שאינו נישום בחיים,
davar she-eino nishum bachayim, something that's not normally given value in life,
לא גזרו רבנן, lo gazru rabanan, they did not, they did not
prohibit. So number one, that's why you're allowed to sell the leather
and the horns and so on. That doesn't mean it has no
value, obviously leather has a lot of value, but it's not the
primary value of the animal. And therefore you're allowed to sell that.
Once you're allowed to sell that, you can also do this trick
of selling the meat as a gift. That's number one. And number
two, that's by a normal
person, non-יתומים. yetomim. וביתמי, u-ve-yatmei, and in the יתמי yetmei example, the
orphan
example, אוקמוה אדאורייתא, okmuha a-de-oraita, then they just said forget about any
restrictions, we'll go back to the biblical law. So אביי Abaye might
be able to say that even selling it after it's dead is
biblically prohibited. The only way you can do it is with orphans
and this work-around. רבא Rava says no, after it's שחט shachted it's
only דרבנן. de-rabanan. So therefore you have two options. One is a
work-around like a free gift. This is a perfect example of a
non-free gift, right? When we say a free gift is very redundant,
of course it's a free gift, a gift is free. No, here's
an example of a non-free gift. Anyway, so you can do it
that way or if it's יתומים yetomim we also waive דרבנן de-rabanan
restrictions. And that's how רבא Rava is reading it.
Yes, using the לולב ואתרוג... lulav ve-etrog... never occurred to me before,
but we always do לולב ואתרוג lulav ve-etrog blah blah blah just
usually the other way around.
Right, exactly, exactly.
Although there nobody claims that the לולב lulav is a gift and
actually there might, you know, what's really happening although not stated is
that there's a fixed price for everything else and the אתרוג etrog
is determining the variable. I don't really think that, well I can
tell you
on the אתרוג etrog they can throw in the other stuff.
That's also true. I don't know exactly how they figure out their
business in that regard.
If you buy an אתרוג etrog by itself it's a gift.
I
will tell you that this last year when, you know, where לולבים
lulavim were, good לולבים lulavim were very hard to come by, right?
There was something about what, importing it from Egypt or something or
whatever. Anyway, so I bought my אתרוג etrog set down on the
Lower East Side from one guy who had the best אתרוגים etrogim
and then I went across the street and bought the אתרוג etrog
set which was much cheaper from another guy but he had better
לולבים. lulavim. So that's where I was able to make my set.
Yes. Anyway, yeah, go ahead.
So are you for the יתומים, yetomim, are you allowed to then
let's say it's a sheep? Yeah. Are you allowed to just let
it live for a while in order to have to sell the
wool? Shear?
No, no, no, no, no, you're definitely absolutely not. You're not allowed
to shear a sheep of a בעל מום, ba'al mum, a פסולי
המוקדשין, psulei ha-mukdashin, absolutely not. And the גמרא Gemara before, yeah, yeah,
yeah, that we're only allowing דרבנן de-rabanan issues, that's
דאורייתא. de-oraita. Even before the גמרא Gemara was very concerned about giving
you too much time because you'll leave it hanging around waiting for
the wool to fall off naturally and
then it'll lead to misuse and so on.
No, no, we're only allowing the sale, that's the only thing we're
allowing. Now the גמרא Gemara says ואף, ve-af, picking up from the
top of ל"ח עמוד א', lamed chet amud aleph,
today's דף, daf, ואף רב שמואל בר רב יצחק סבר לה להא
דרבא. ve-af Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak savar lah le-ha de-Rava. רב
שמואל בר רב יצחק Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak held of רבא
Rava that it's talking about orphans and we allow that straight away.
דאמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק מנין למעשר בהמה של יתומים שמוכרין
אותו כדרכו. de-amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak minayin le-ma'aser behemah shel
yetomim she-mochrin oto ke-darko. How do you know when it comes to
the מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah of orphans you can sell it normally?
So he has the same position but he learned it from a
different verse, not the verse of תמורה tmurah but a different verse.
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, the verse says, רק בכל אות נפשך תזבח ואכלת בשר,
rak be-chol avat nafshecha tizbach ve-achalta vasar, with all the desire of
your soul you shall slaughter and eat meat, כברכת ה' אלהיך. ke-virkat
Hashem Elokecha. It's interesting, here the גמרא Gemara does not have the
next phrase which is part of the דרשה, drasha, as the blessing
of Hashem your God that He has given to you. And this
is understood, it's a question what the context is, but according to
many this is understood in the context of an animal of a
בכור bechor or מעשר ma'aser that has a מום, mum, that has
a blemish. Don't worry, you don't have to redeem it, you don't
have to bring it as a קרבן, korban, you can שחט shacht
it, eat it at your heart's content, כצבי וכאיל, ka-tzvi ve-cha-ayal,
like the deer, wherever you might be, you can be טמא tamei
and so on. Once it has a blemish, שחט shacht it and
eat it. Okay, very nice. How does that tell me you can
sell it? So now let's take a look. It says כברכת ה'
אלהיך, ke-virkat Hashem Elokecha, like the blessing of Hashem your God. איזהו
דבר שאין בו ברכה מחיים אלא לאחר שחיטה? eizehu davar she-ein bo
bracha me-chayim ela le-achar shechitah? So it says you shall slaughter it
as God has blessed you. So what type of a thing will
you have, will the blessing only come after you've slaughtered it? הוי
אומר זה מעשר בהמה. hevei omer zeh ma'aser behemah. It's מעשר בהמה.
ma'aser behemah. What does that mean? So it means that we know
that when it's alive you're basically not allowed to do anything with
it, right? You can't sell it, you can't shear it, whatever. But
after you שחט shacht it, then you can eat it. But his
דרשה drasha is not only can you eat it, it says then
you're really blessed with it. So to really be blessed with it
goes beyond allowing you to eat it. So what can you do
after it's שחט shachted other than eat it? Well, you can sell
it. So based on the fact that we say כברכת ke-virkat and
that's talking about when you שחט shachted it, that's how we understand
that you can even
sell it in the marketplace.
Right, that's true about the משנה, Mishnah, but you can sell it
out of your home. Okay, so therefore biblically it's permitted, normally דרבנן-ly
de-rabanan we restrict it, but we waive that for orphans. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara goes to the הבלעה havla'ah case, which again according
to רבא Rava would mean even in a non-orphan case. איבעיא להו,
iba'ya lehu, they raised the question, מהו הבלעה בעצמות? mahu havla'ah be-atzmot?
We mentioned... absorbed its cost in the skin, okay, and the fat.
What about the bones? Like, could you just say, I'll sell you
the bones and throw in the meat? Is bones, is that like
does that get, you know, is that too farcical so that we
can't we could not even do that with a straight face? Would
people ever pay anything for the bones? People will pay for the
skin and the fat. So will they ever really pay for the
bones that you could say, oh, I'm just buying the bones and
the meat was thrown in? Yes.
Bones always have a small amount of meat in them.
That's a good point, maybe minus the marrow, I guess. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says.
It's a good question whether in the rabbinic restriction of not selling
the, you know, not selling the meat, did they include the marrow
of the bones? I don't know the answer to that. Anyway, let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. So it says רבי חייא ורבי
שמעון ברבי, Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi, it's a debate of
רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי. Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi. חד
אמר מבליעו, chad amar mavlei'o, you can absorb it, וחד אמר אין
מבליעו, v'chad amar ein mavlei'o, you cannot. ולא פליגי, v'lo pligi, they
don't debate. הא בדקה הא בגסה. ha b'daka ha b'gasa. It's a
question about sheep or cow. Sheep, normally people do not do anything
with the bones of a sheep, but the bones of a cow
are definitely used. They're big, they're hard, they're used for making various
types of vessels, right, of bone, you know, whenever they do these
archaeological digs, right, there's always these types of like bone, you know,
bone vessels. So those are definitely used. He's got an ear for
Galitzia.
Okay, and those are definitely used.
So therefore, you can do a sale of the bones and give
this as a gift. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it eima, if you want, you
could say אידי ואידי בגסה, adi v'adi b'gasa, they're both talking about
a cow, ולא פליגי, v'lo pligi, and they're also not really debating.
מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה, mar k'atrai u'mar k'atrai, each one
is going by their own location, by their own locale. In one,
in one of the rabbi's place, they used bones for making vessels,
and therefore it was a reasonable thing to claim to be selling,
and in the other, they would never do that. גופא. gufa. Okay,
now let's get back to the verses by בכור bechor and מעשר
ma'aser where we know, where we're going to learn that you cannot
sell מעשר, ma'aser, although as we've seen, we are basically saying you
only can't sell it when it's alive. But let's go back and
look at the ברייתא braita and look at the verses. בבכור הוא
אומר, b'bechor hu omer, by בכור bechor it says לא יפדה, lo
yipadeh, cannot be redeemed. But therefore, don't redeem it, but you can
sell it. ונמכר, v'nimkar, it can be sold. במעשר נאמר לא יגאל,
b'ma'aser ne'emar lo yiga'el, also cannot be redeemed, except a different phrase.
ואינו נמכר, v'eino nimkar, and it can't be sold. לא חי ולא
שחוט, lo chai v'lo shachut, not alive or slaughtered, although again, we've
been saying אביי Abaye aside that שחוט shachut is only rabbinic. ולא
תם ולא בעל מום, v'lo tam v'lo ba'al mum, whether with or
without a blemish. So מנלן הני מילי, minalan hanei mili, where do
you get this from that לא יגאל lo yiga'el by מעשר ma'aser
means don't sell it? So אמר רב חנינא אמר רב וכן אמר
רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rav Chanina amar Rav v'chen amar
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, נאמר לא יגאל במעשר, ne'emar lo yiga'el
b'ma'aser, it says by מעשר ma'aser it cannot be redeemed, ונאמר לא
יגאל בחרמים, v'ne'emar lo yiga'el b'charamim, and it says by חרמים, charamim,
right, חרמים charamim is an interesting thing, the Torah never spells out
what חרם cherem is, but it's some type of sanctified something to
God by making it a חרם, cherem, which is like banning it,
somehow making it forbidden, but there's also a sense of sanctifying it
to God. And the Torah says
כל חרם לא יגאל ולא ימכר קדש קדשים הוא להשם, kol cherem
lo yiga'el v'lo yimacher kodesh kodashim hu l'Hashem, or הוא להשם. hu
l'Hashem. Any חרם cherem cannot be redeemed and cannot be sold, it
is holy of holies to God. So there, cannot be redeemed and
cannot be sold are juxtaposed. So there, the יגאל yiga'el becomes the,
you know, the link to tell us לא יגאל lo yiga'el comes
with לא ימכר, lo yimacher, cannot be sold. So if that's true
about חרם, cherem, it's going to be true about מעשר. ma'aser. So
the גמרא Gemara says מה להלן מכירה עמו, ma hallan mechira imo,
the same way there selling is combined with redeeming and cannot be
done with redeeming, אף כאן מכירה עמו, af kan mechira imo, here
too selling is combined with redeeming, the same way you can't redeem
מעשר, ma'aser, you cannot sell it. So that's the דרשה. drasha. Now
we're going to, now we're going to challenge that. אמר ליה רב
נחמן בר יצחק לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, amar lei Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak l'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, מופני, mufni, not מפני, mipnei,
מופני, mufni,
it must be open, it must be unattached. What does that mean?
That when you make a גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, you connect לא
יגאל lo yiga'el to לא יגאל, lo yiga'el, the question is if
that word is really needed in its location, then it's not really
free to say, oh, it's coming to connect into a גזירה שוה.
gezeira shava. Okay, and therefore, sometimes you can make a גזירה שוה
gezeira shava even if the word is being used, but then it's
much more open to critique, and any logical critique of the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava will break the link. Only if the word is
really seen as extra does it say that now I can make
the link and say that's its whole purpose is to make the
link, and logical question will not break it. Okay, so without the
link, it's more like, without the word being extra, it's more like
an analogy and it's open to critique. With the word being extra,
it's really like a direct link and it's telling you to apply
the laws and logical critique is not relevant. So he says it's
got to be that this word is extra. אי לא מופני, ei
lo mufni, if it weren't extra, there's a lot to critique here,
this comparison. How would I critique it? איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach, you
could ask,
מה לחרמים שכן חלים על הכל, ma l'charamim sheken chalim al hakol,
that חרמים charamim maybe is more
restrictive, why is חרמים charamim is more weighty, because it applies to
all things. What does it mean applies to all things? So רשי,
Rashi, as opposed to מעשר. ma'aser. So רשי Rashi says there's two
points of contrast, number one is that a חרם cherem you could
actually to חרם cherem *cherem* and something that's already sanctified. Very, very
bizarre, you can almost never do that, sanctify something that's already sanctified,
but you can by חרם cherem *cherem*. And that shows again how
weighty it is. The other thing Rashi says, of simpler point, is
that מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* only applies to every tenth animal. You could
do a חרם cherem *cherem* on any animal and anything. So therefore
חרם cherem *cherem* has a larger scope and is weightier, and therefore
maybe the restriction is limit of selling is limited to חרם cherem
*cherem*. Okay, so that's you can't make the comparison. So לאפנויי מאפנויי
*le'afnuyei me'afnuyei*, which one is open? It's only one of the words,
the links has to be open. לא יגאל lo yigael *lo yiga'el*
it shall not be redeemed. So which one is it? The word,
that phrase by מעשר maaser *ma'aser* or that phrase by חרמים charamim?
*charamim*? Let's take a look. לא lo, יאמר לא יגאל lo yigael
בחרמים *lo yomar lo yiga'el becharamim*. Don't say it by חרמים charamim?
*charamim*. It's, let me try to demonstrate that it's extra by חרמים
charamim, *charamim*. How is that? ויגמר ממעשר *veyigamer mima'aser*. I could have
learned that out from מעשר maaser. *ma'aser*. Let it just say מעשר
maaser. *ma'aser* can't be redeemed, and of course I'll say it's certainly
true by חרם cherem *cherem*. Why? Because of a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer *kal vachomer* you just said. מה מעשר maaser. קודש kodesh ואינו
נגאל *mah ma'aser kodesh ve'eino niga'al*, the same way מעשר maaser *ma'aser*
is sanctified, holy, and cannot be redeemed, אף חרמים charamim. קדשים ואינם
נגאלים *af charamim kodashim ve'einam nigalim*, the same is true by חרמים
charamim? *charamim*. So A, it's an analogy and B, not only an
analogy, maybe it's even a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* because you just
got through proving that חרם cherem *cherem* is weightier. So just say
don't redeem מעשר maaser. *ma'aser* and I'll apply it to חרם cherem,
*cherem*, so you don't have to tell me by it by חרם
cherem *cherem*. If you are telling me, it's the word is extra.
So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s going to say, one minute, you cannot
necessarily have learned it out from מעשר maaser *ma'aser*. אף חרמים charamim,
קדשים ואינם נגאלים *af charamim kodashim ve'einam nigalim*, so first here's the
end of that thought. ולא יגאל דכתב רחמנא למה לי *velo yiga'el
dechasa rachamana lamah li*? So why does it say לא יגאל lo
yigael. *lo yiga'el* by חרם cherem, *cherem* if I could have learned
out the restriction of redeeming from מעשר maaser *ma'aser*? לאפנויי *le'afnuyei*, to
make it extra and to allow me to link them about the,
to tell me the teaching about selling. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says no, no, no, you can't do that. איכא למפרך *ika lemifrach*.
I could challenge that, that you can't learn one from the other
about redeeming. מה למעשר שכן קדש לפניו ולאחריו *mah lema'aser sheken kadesh
lefanav ule'acharayiv*. מעשר maaser *ma'aser* has a way that it's, it's stronger
than חרם cherem *cherem*. מעשר maaser *ma'aser* before and after becomes sanctified,
not automatically but accidentally. If you're counting the animals and you accidentally
count the ninth one as tenth, or the eleventh one as tenth,
they also become קדוש *kadosh*, even though that was unintentional, and normally
we say that if you sanctify something by error, it's not sanctified.
So there's a way in which מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* is weightier and
therefore you cannot apply what you know from חרם cherem. *cherem* to
מעשר maaser *ma'aser*. חרם cherem? *cherem* has one aspect that's weightier. You
can't apply what you know from מעשר maaser *ma'aser* to חרם cherem,
*cherem* because מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* has one aspect that's weightier. So how
can you tell me saying don't redeem is extra? You could not
have learned it out on מעשר maaser? *ma'aser*. There's a way in
which מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* is weightier. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says,
אלא *ela*, let's try this way. Not the opposite, this way. לא
יאמר לא יגאל lo yigael במעשר
*lo yomar lo yiga'el bema'aser*, and I'll learn out not redeeming it
not from מעשר maaser *ma'aser*, I'll learn it out from a different
thing. ויגמר העברה העברה havarah havarah, מבכור *veyigamer ha'avarah ha'avarah mibechor*. I'll
learn it out from בכור bechor, *bechor*. בכור bechor *bechor* also can't
be redeemed. מה בכור bechor, קודש kodesh, ואינו נגאל *mah bechor kodesh
ve'eino niga'al*, the same way בכור bechor *bechor* is holy and cannot
be redeemed, אף חרמים קדשים ואינם נגאלים *af charamim kodashim ve'einam nigalim*,
the same is true by חרם cherem. *cherem*. And therefore because I
could have learned it from בכור bechor *bechor*, לא יגאל lo yigael
*lo yiga'el* is extra. לא יגאל lo yigael. דכתב רחמנא במעשר למה
לי *lo yiga'el dechasa rachamana bema'aser lamah li*? Why does the תורה
Torah *Torah* have to say by מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* don't redeem it
if I could have learned it out from בכור bechor *bechor*? לאפנויי
*le'afnuyei*, to make it extra and therefore to allow this גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah *gezerah shavah*. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, you can't do
that either. איכא למפרך *ika lemifrach*. You can challenge. מה לבכור שכן
קדושתו מרחם *mah lebechor sheken kedushato merachem*. בכור bechor *bechor* has a
way that it's weightier. The animal is, it has קדושה kedusha *kedushah*
from the moment that it's born without an act of sanctifying it,
right? Everything else needs an act to sanctify. So all these things
have distinctive characteristics. חרמים *charamim* apply to everything, בכור bechor. *bechor* has
an automatic sanctity, מעשר maaser. *ma'aser* sanctifies before and after, and therefore
you can't tell me that I could learn one from the other
and that something is extra because each one of them is distinctive
and therefore I could not have learned one from the other. I
can't do a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezerah shavah*. Thank God the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* is not doing that here. It could have done
that, but the גמרא Gemara *gemara* did not need to do that
here. You could go try to figure out a סברא *sevara* that
could work. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* does. So the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this. Where were we? אלא לא יאמר
לא יגאל lo yigael במעשר *ela lo yomar lo yiga'el bema'aser*. So
fine, so it has to say לא יגאל lo yigael בחרמים *lo
yiga'el becharamim*. But it didn't have to say don't redeem it by
מעשר maaser *ma'aser*. Why not? ויגמר העברה haavara העברה haavara, מבכור *veyigamer
ha'avarah ha'avarah mibechor*. Because I could have learned out, it says both
by מעשר maaser *ma'aser* and בכור bechor *bechor* uses the word העברה
haavara *ha'avarah*, you shall pass it over, hand it over. So the
same, so therefore by בכור bechor *bechor* I know you can't redeem
it, so I could have learned out by מעשר maaser *ma'aser* you
can't redeem it based on the connection of העברה havarah. *ha'avarah*. And
therefore saying not to redeem מעשר maaser *ma'aser* is extra to allow
me to link it to חרם cherem. *cherem* and say that it
means don't sell. מה בכור bechor קודש kodesh. ואינו נגאל אף מעשר
ma'aser, קודש ואינו נגאל *mah bechor kodesh ve'eino niga'al af ma'aser kodesh
ve'eino niga'al*. So the same way בכור bechor *bechor* you cannot redeem,
you can't redeem מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*. So therefore לא יגאל lo yigael
דכתב רחמנא במעשר למה לי *lo yiga'el dechasa rachamana bema'aser lamah li*?
Why does the תורה Torah *Torah* have to say by מעשר ma'aser,
*ma'aser* don't redeem it if I could have learned it out from
בכור bechor, *bechor*? לאפנויי *le'afnuyei*, to make it extra and allow me
to learn out not to sell it. The גמרא Gemara *gemara* says
one minute, you still can't learn מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser* from בכור bechor,
*bechor*. ואכתי במעשר לא מפני *ve'achti bema'aser lo mofnei*. You can't say
מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser* that it's extra. דאיכא למפרך כדאמרן *de'ika lemifrach kide'amran*.
You have the question we asked before. בכור bechor, *bechor* has a
distinctive character, בכור bechor *bechor* is automatic. So how can you learn
מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser* from בכור bechor *bechor*? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says no. והעברת קרא יתירה הוא hu *veha'avarta kra yeseira hu*. We're
not learning it by analogy. We have an extra verse. It says
both by מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser*... the phrase העברה by בכור, bechor, it
says the phrase העברה by מעשר, ma'aser? pass it, pass it over.
That allows us to link בכור bechor, and מעשר Ma'aser even though
they're not exactly the same. They're close, it allows us to link
them and to
say that if you can't redeem
בכור, bechor you can't redeem מעשר. ma'aser. So say there's no need
to say don't redeem מעשר. ma'aser, If it says it, it makes
it extra and allows us to now free that up to link
it to חרם cherem. and say what it really means is also
don't sell מעשר. ma'aser, Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, you
see Bobby you came back for the right דף. daf. Good thing
you weren't here yesterday, we were so boring. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on and says, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, בכור נמי נילף גאולה גאולה מחרמים. bechor nami neilaf geulah geulah
mecharamim. Fine, you've proven your point. We've got לא יגאל lo yiga'el.
as extra by מעשר ma'aser. and it's linked to חרם cherem? and
it means don't sell. But now it's saying like this, by בכור
bechor. let's also make a similar type of a connection. Let's say
by בכור bechor it says לא יפדה lo yipadeh which essentially means
don't redeem it. So why not link בכור bechor also to חרם
cherem? and say don't redeem by בכור bechor links to don't redeem
by חרם cherem and also means don't sell? And we'll say like
this, דמעשר מפני דבכור לא מפני. demaser mafni debechor lo mafni. No,
because we've got remember, we freed up the word לא יגאל lo
yiga'el by מעשר. ma'aser, We didn't free it up by בכור. bechor
So that's why we can't link by בכור bechor because the word
isn't freed up. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, free it up.
ומאי חזית דלא יפדה דבכור לגופיה ודמעשר לאהנויי. umai chazis delo yipadeh
debechor leguifeih udemaser leahanoyei. What makes you think that the לא יפדה
lo yipadeh that the not redeeming starts with בכור bechor, and therefore
it's not needed by מעשר ma'aser and it's freed up by מעשר
ma'aser to tell me it means don't sell? ודמעשר לאהנויי. udemaser leahanoyei.
And the phrase by מעשר ma'aser, is freed up? So right, by
בכור bechor it says לא יפדה, lo yipadeh, by מעשר ma'aser it
says לא יגאל. lo yiga'el What we basically said is you can
learn from בכור bechor. to מעשר, ma'aser, so we start with בכור,
bechor, don't redeem, frees up the phrase by מעשר ma'aser. which now
allows us to say by מעשר ma'aser? don't sell. So it says
just do the opposite, start by מעשר, ma'aser, don't redeem it, say
you link it to בכור, bechor? free up the phrase by בכור,
bechor and now say בכור bechor, means you can't sell. How do
you determine to free up this phrase by מעשר? ma'aser We have,
it says לא יפדה lo yipadeh by בכור bechor and לא יגאל
lo yiga'el by מעשר, which basically means the same thing. So we
really say one of them is extra. Say it by one, it's
linked to the other by העברה, so the other gets freed up.
So you start by בכור, it's linked, העברה gets freed up, and
now we use that to say מעשר it's linked to חרם cherem
means don't sell it. Why not do the opposite? Start by מעשר,
link it, free it up by בכור, and now link that to
חרם and say don't sell בכור rather than don't sell מעשר. Well,
it's not which one comes first, let's read the answer and then
I'll take the question because the answer is pretty straightforward. The גמרא
Gemara says, ואימא דמעשר לגופיה ודבכור לאהנויי. veaima demaser leguifeih udebechor leahanoyei.
So the מעשר is what's needed, it's freed up by בכור. גמרא
Gemara says, no. דנין גאולה מגאולה ואין דנין פדייה מגאולה. danin geulah
migeulah veein danin pidyah migeulah. No, cause it's true they both have
the same sense, but by מעשר it says לא יגאל lo yiga'el
and by בכור it says לא יפדה. lo yipadeh. And what's the
phrase it uses by חרמים? לא יגאל. lo yiga'el So we obviously
are have a desire to free up מעשר and to link מעשר
to חרם cause by both of them it says לא יגאל lo
yiga'el, and we are not so interested in freeing up בכור where
it says לא יפדה lo yipadeh which means the same as לא
יגאל lo yiga'el. but it's phrased differently. So we'd rather link the
same phrase. Just one more minute and I'll take your question. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka mina? What does
it matter? It means the same thing. התני דבי רבי ישמעאל. hatni
devei Rabbi Yishmael. We taught from רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the גמרא
Gemara loves bringing in this ברייתא. braita. ובא הכהן uva hakohen ושב
הכהן. veshav hakohen. By נגעים negayim it says the כהן, kohen, one
פסוק pasuk says he comes, the other says he returns, and basically
it means they mean the same thing, he goes to the house.
זו היא שיבה זו היא ביאה. zu hi shivah zu hi biah.
It means the same thing and therefore it makes a גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah from them even though the words are different because the
sense is the same. So you see you can make it based
on sense. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, הני מילי היכא דליכא
דדמי ליה. hani mili heicha deka dedami leih. That's when there's not
a better something that's more similar. Then maybe we can connect them
based on similar meaning. אבל היכא דאיכא דדמי ליה, aval heicha deika
dedami leih, when there's a phrase that is much more similar, the
exact same phrase לא יגאל לא יגאל, lo yigael lo yigael, מדדמי
ליה ילפינן, mididami leih yalfinan, where am I? אל מדדמי ליה ילפינן,
al mididami leih yalfinan, we'd rather link it to the exact same
phrase. So basically now the פשט pshat is, we link מעשר לא
יגאל maaser lo yigael to the לא יגאל lo yiga'el of חרם,
which basically says there it means don't sell, here it means don't
sell, because it's the exact same phrase we want to make that
link. How do we free up that word? We free up that
word by telling me it could have been learned from בכור and
therefore this word is extra and it's freed up to make this
link that we want to because of the same phrase. You had
a question Charlie? Yeah, isn't there a principle that you can't just
create a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. based on logic, that you need
to have been taught it by your teachers going all the way
back to משה מסיני? Moshe miSinai? You mean, so how does the
גמרא Gemara here consider maybe we did it this way, maybe we
did it that way? So that's a very good question. So the
רמב"ן Ramban asks that in his השגות Hasagos to the רמב"ם ספר
המצוות, Rambam Sefer Hamitzvos, and he... Basically asks like from a lot
of cases like this, what do you mean you need a מסורה?
mesorah? I mean, the גמרא Gemara says don't make גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah. this way, make it that way. And רמב"ן Ramban says what
we must say is that when the גמרא Gemara says you need
a מסורה mesorah it means that you really just know the הלכה
halacha from מסורה mesorah and you have a מסורה mesorah that this
הלכה halacha can be derived from גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah But you
still then have latitude to try to figure out how to make
the גזירה שוה. gezeira shava, Okay, but it's a very good point.
The גמרא Gemara does definitely at times think that make it seem
like גזירה שוה gezeira shava is more open for figuring it out
yourself, and therefore the רמב"ן Ramban says that מסורה mesorah has to
be therefore reinterpreted more broadly. Yes. You know, it's funny, I would
have thought that, you know, just instead of trying to like figure
out, well, what do we learn, how do we learn it, just,
you know, say what you mean by each one of them and
then like that's the משנה. Mishnah. Oy, there goes all the, all
of the, you know, things that are ever learned from a לימוד.
limud. I mean, if the תורה Torah wanted to say it, it
would have said it explicitly. You know, there's, let's throw out all
of the מדרשים. midrashim. Okay, I don't have that, I don't have
an answer to that. Let's go on. So that's the גמרא Gemara
here. Now, the point is if it would have said it, we
wouldn't have had the fun, exactly, we wouldn't have had the fun
of תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh of learning. Now, the גמרא
Gemara continues. Now, that's how we know you can't sell מעשר, but
again, we have, we haven't defined that that is limited to when
the בעלים be'alim is alive, at least according to everybody other than
אביי. Abaye. Let's take a look. So the גמרא says like this.
ולילף בכור העברה העברה ממעשר. Veleilef bechor havarah havarah mima'aser. Now, fuck.
Now you've said מעשר you can't sell. Okay, but now that we
have that through מעשר, let's use the pipeline that it's connected to
בכור from this word העברה העברה, and the same way בכור taught
us that you can't redeem by מעשר, let מעשר go and teach
that you can't sell by בכור, right? Because those two are connected
at the hip by this word העברה. Okay, so now, העברה העברה
ממעשר דמעשר נמי גמר גאולה גאולה מחרמים. Havarah havarah mima'aser dima'aser nami
gamar geulah geulah micharamim. If it says by מעשר we learn from
חרם גאולה geulah means don't sell, so now apply that to בכור
and say don't sell a בכור. So the גמרא says no. מי
איכא רחמנא גבי חרמים הוא. Mi ika rachmana gabei charamim hu. But
the תורה Torah says by חרם, קודש קודשים הוא, kodesh kodashim hu,
it is holy of holies. הוא ולא בכור. Hu velo bechor. This
is limited, this restriction doesn't apply to all things. It applies only
to חרם and מעשר, but not to בכור, because הוא hu is
a limiting word. So the גמרא says, אימא הוא ולא מעשר. eima
hu velo ma'aser. So why not restrict מעשר? No, מעשר גאולה כמוהו.
ma'aser geulah kamoho. מעשר we link by the same word לא יגאל.
lo yiga'el, Okay, so לא יגאל lo yiga'el connects it, הוא limits
it, don't take it any further, and that's how you know don't
sell מעשר. רבא אמר. Rava amar. So now רבא Rava has a
whole different approach. לא יגאל דחרמים לא צריך. Lo yiga'el decharamim lo
tzarich. You're saying לא יגאל lo yiga'el was extra by מעשר, no,
לא יגאל lo yiga'el is extra by חרם. How's it extra by
חרם? How would I have known you can't redeem חרמים? Because דאיתנהו
היכא. de'isneihu heicha. Where is this, where do you think you might
be trying to redeem this anyway to begin with? אי בבעלים, Ei
bibe'alim, if you still are holding onto the חרם, הקדש נינהו. hekdesh
ninhu. It's הקדש, hekdesh, and of course you can't redeem it. Now,
of course this has a what? Of course הקדש hekdesh you can
redeem, right? If it's not a קרבן, korban, the whole point of
הקדש hekdesh is you're allowed to redeem it. What does it mean
you can't redeem it? So רש"י Rashi said because of this and
because of other problems, רש"י Rashi changes the גירסא girsa here. And
he says רבא Rava doesn't say that it didn't have to say
לא יגאל lo yiga'el by חרמים, it didn't have to say לא
ימכר lo yimacher by חרמים. The תורה Torah never had to tell
me that I can't sell חרם. I sanctified my car. Of course
I can't sell it. I just gave it over to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Why does it have to tell me don't sell
it, right? I mean, it's not mine. It's not mine. So that's
what it means. It's not mine, of course I can't sell it.
אי בכהנים. Ei bechohanim. Now, there's a whole question what do you
do with חרמים? Does the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash get it, does
the כהן kohen get it? There are two פסוקים pesukim that actually
say different things. And the question is how to interpret it. So
one way we say it is a very bizarre status of חרם.
It's קודש and sanctified when it's in my house, if I misuse
it, מעילה, me'ilah, whatever, it's real קודש, but then I hand it
over to the כהן, kohen, and as soon as I hand it
over to the כהן, kohen, it's no longer קודש. It's חולין. chullin.
Okay, that's one way of resolving those פסוקים, pesukim, which רבא Rava
is assuming. Why is that? Because one פסוק pasuk says כל חרם
קודש קודשים הוא להשם, kol cherem kodesh kodashim hu l'Hashem, and the
other פסוק pasuk says by the כהנים, kohanim, כל חרם בישראל לך
יהיה, kol cherem b'Yisrael lecha yihyeh, you get the חרם. So which
is it? Do they get it or does God get it? So
one explanation, one way of resolving it is that it's קודש קודשים.
kodesh kodashim. One way is that one of them is the default
and the other is if you specify. The default is one, if
you specify it's the other. But another way of resolving this contradiction
is by saying that it's קודש קודשים kodesh kodashim while I still
have it, and as soon as I hand it over, it then
transfers its status. Okay, are you asking the deeper why, like the
religious why? That I don't know. Well, we can talk about it
after. No questions, I'm sorry, I'm not taking questions out. What? You're
saying קדשי מזבח גבוה חזקו מהם? kodshei mizbei'ach gavoha chazku meihem? No.
Yeah, but it doesn't work that way by קרבנות, korbanos, it doesn't
become חולין. chullin. Here it really becomes חולין. chullin. So it's a
very bizarre thing. I do not have a full explanation now, maybe
when we get to ערכין, Erchin, where it'll be our direct place
to talk about it, we can reflect on that more. Okay, so
therefore רבא Rava is saying, reading this like רש"י, Rashi, when is
it that you can't sell? If the תורה Torah has to say
don't sell it, if I haven't given it to the כהן, kohen,
of course I can't sell it. It's not mine. I sanctified it.
So אי ב... Ei be... כהן kohen and if now the כהן
kohen has it, חולין נינהו, chullin ninhu, then of course he can
sell it, it loses all of its status. דתניא detanya we teach
in a ברייתא, braita, חרמים, what's the story with חרם? כל זמן
שהם בבית בעלים kol zman sheheim b'veit ba'alim under my control, הרי
הן כהקדש לכל דבריהם, harei hein k'hekdesh l'chol divreihem, they're like הקדש,
hekdesh, שנאמר, shenemar, כל חרם קדש קדשים הוא לה', kol cherem kodesh
kodashim hu l'Hashem, they're holy of holies to God. נתנו לכהן, netanu
l'kohen, as soon as I gave it to the כהן, kohen, הרי
הן כחולין לכל דבריהם, harei hein k'chullin l'chol divreihem, they're totally de-sanctified,
שנאמר, shenemar, כל חרם בישראל לך יהיה, kol cherem b'Yisrael l'cha yihiyeh,
totally yours. So therefore I don't need to tell me don't sell
it. In one case when the כהן kohen has it, I can't
sell it, when I have it, it's, it doesn't even get off
the ground. So I don't need that restriction, that prohibition. So therefore
לא, I'm reading it like רש''י, Rashi, not לא יגאל lo yiga'el
but לא ימכר. lo yimacher. וכתב רחמנא למה לי? v'chtav rachmana lama
li? Why does the תורה Torah have to tell me don't sell
חרם? אם אינו ענין לחרמים, im eino inyan l'charamim, if it's not
needed for the חרם case itself, תנהו ענין למעשר, tneihu inyan l'ma'aser,
apply it to מעשר, which is again linked by the word לא
יגאל, lo yiga'el but here rather than making a גזירה שוה, what
רש''י Rashi is saying is take this extra prohibition which really isn't
needed and apply it to מעשר. Okay. Now, אימא תנהו ענין לבכור,
eima tneihu inyan l'bechor, so why apply it to מעשר, why not
apply it to בכור? No, מעשר גאולה כמותו, ma'aser geulah k'moto, there
it is because of the similar phrase of לא יגאל. Okay, so
that's again how you know that מעשר cannot be sold, again, when
it's alive, but בכור can be. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi,
אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi says, לא יגאל דמעשר לא ימכר
הוא. lo yiga'el d'ma'aser lo yimacher hu. רב אשי Rav Ashi says
probably what we all would have thought the גמרא meant originally. Says
who needs this whole גזירה שוה etcetera? This says no, the word
לא יגאל by מעשר we're going to interpret based on the way
it appears by חרם to actually mean don't sell, doesn't mean don't
redeem. Now, how do you take it out of its simple sense?
So אמר רב אשי מנא אמינא לה, amar Rav Ashi m'na amina
lah, how do I know this? דכתיב, d'chtiv, the verse says, והיה
הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש, v'hayah hu u'tmurato yihiyeh kodesh, this is what
it says by מעשר, it and its exchange will be holy, לא
יגאל, it cannot be redeemed. So אימא סיפא תמורה, eima seifa tmura,
when it says it talks about a תמורה, tmura, an exchange, when
do you make the, can you do you do that? Again, you're
not allowed to, but when is it talking about? מחיים, mechayim, when
it's alive. So remember, this is also how he said that selling
is limited to when it's alive and not when it's dead. But
now the verse actually says תמורה tmura and then it says don't
redeem it. So אימא סיפא אינו נגאל, eima seifa eino nig'al, so
then applying that to the literal sense of the word redeem would
mean when can it not be redeemed? מחיים, mechayim, when it's alive.
הא לאחר שחיטה נגאל, ha l'achar shechita nig'al, which would suggest that
you can redeem it after it's been שחט. shechted. But how could
you redeem it after it's been שחט? shechted? הבעיא העמדה והערכה. haba'aya
ha'amada v'ha'aracha. It's a קרבן korban that's been שחט, shechted, right? And
and therefore it needs to stand up, there's no way you can
redeem it once it's been שחט. shechted. So here's the point, I'm
going to prove to you לא יגאל means don't sell. Because since
I'm going to interpret by context that לא יגאל is limited to
when it's alive, that would make sense if the word meant don't
sell. Don't sell once it's alive, sell when it's dead, which is
what we said before. But if the word means don't redeem it,
that doesn't make sense. That means don't redeem it when it's alive,
redeem it when it's dead. I can't redeem it when it's dead
anyway. It needs to be alive to even have the possibility of
redeeming it. And the reason why it says לא יגאל instead of
לא ימכר? lo yimacher? אלא שמע מינה לא יגאל לא ימכר הוא.
ela shma mina lo yiga'el lo yimacher hu. So we see that
לא יגאל really means don't sell it and then don't sell it
you could say means don't sell it when it's alive but sell
it when it's dead. גמרא says, הניחא למאן דאמר קדשי מזבח היו
בכלל העמדה והערכה. hanicha l'man d'amar kodshei mizbe'ach hayu bichlal ha'amada v'ha'aracha.
That's good if you say things that were sanctified to the altar
need to be stood up to be to be redeemed. So obviously
it cannot be applying after it's dead. אלא למאן דאמר קדשי מזבח
לא היו בכלל העמדה והערכה מאי איכא למימר? ela l'man d'amar kodshei
mizbe'ach lo hayu bichlal ha'amada v'ha'aracha mai ika l'meimar? But if things
that are sanctified to the altar can be dead when you redeem
them, then your whole point falls through. So גמרא says, no, אנן
הכי קאמרינן, anan hachi kaamrinan, and here's what we mean that it
can't be talking after it's dead. מי איכא דמחיים לא מיפרק לאחר
שחיטה מיפרק? mi ika d'mechayim lo mifrak l'achar shechita mifrak? Even if
you could redeem some things when they're dead, what type of a
thing would the תורה Torah say don't redeem it when it's alive
but yes redeem it when it's dead? Okay, what we never would
find something that would be more available to be redeemed after it
died than when it was still alive. So the גמרא says, אלמה
לא, almah lo, why not? אלמה לא, almah lo, why not? מחיים
דאלימא קדושתיה לא מיפרק לאחר שחיטה דאקילא קדושתיה מיפרק. mechayim d'alima kedushatei
lo mifrak l'achar shechita d'akila kedushatei mifrak. Maybe when it's alive the
קדושה kedusha is very strong because when it's alive this מעשר you
can't use it, right? And and therefore if the קדושה kedusha is
strong you can't redeem it. Whereas after it's died, the קדושה kedusha
isn't as strong, it's meat and you can eat the meat, it's
more allowed for you to use, and therefore maybe it's more available
to be redeemed. So the גמרא says, no no no, וכל דכן
הוא, v'chol d'kan hu, it's a קל וחומר the opposite way. I
agree with you the קדושה kedusha is stronger when it's alive, but
stronger קדושה kedusha does not mean you can't redeem it. The opposite
makes sense. ומה מחיים דאלים למיפס פדיון, u'mah mechayim d'alim l'mifas pidyon,
if it's alive the קדושה kedusha is strong, a strong קדושה kedusha
would mean that it can it can take take take, transfer, take
possession of other money, it can it can also extend to other
things, and that would allow it to be redeemed. לא מיפרק, lo
mifrak, and even so you can't redeem it. לאחר שחיטה דלא אלים
למיפס פדיון, l'achar shechita d'lo alim l'mifas pidyon, after it's שחט shechted
that the קדושה Kedusha, is weaker, so weaker. Stronger קדושה, Kedusha it's
a very interesting concept the גמרא has, that stronger קדושה Kedusha does
not mean it can't be redeemed, right? You can have something that's
קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, Holy of Holies, as long as it's not
a קרבן korban you can redeem it. Stronger קדושה Kedusha means, you
know, if it's so strong it's like this force, this power, and
therefore it can transfer from object to object. Where if the קדושה
Kedusha, is very weak, right, it doesn't have the power to move
around so much. It's much more if you would sort of connected
to the thing that it's in. For some reason I'm thinking about,
well, I'm thinking about the early Harry Potters and Voldemort when he
was still very weak, you know, what he was able to do
when he took possession of somebody else. Anyway, my kids listen to
that stuff non-stop. Anyway, so if it's weaker, if it's weaker it
can't be transferred as much. So how could the תורה say don't
redeem it when it's alive and you could redeem it when it's
weak? The opposite makes sense. Okay, דלאו מפידיונם מיפרק, d'lav mipidyonam mifrak,
אלא שמע מינה, ela shma mina, from this you see, לא יגאל
לא ימכר. lo yiga'el lo yimacher. If the תורה is saying don't
do it when it's alive, do it after it's dead, that cannot
be true about קדושה, it has to be and redeeming, it has
to be true about selling. Don't sell it when it's alive, but
you can sell it when it's dead, which reinforces what we said
before, and that's how we know לא יגאל really means don't sell.
So now the גמרא asks Michael's question, וליכתוב רחמנא לא ימכר. v'lichtov
rachmana lo yimacher. And that's finally, we get Michael's, so then just
say what you mean! Say don't sell it! Why say don't redeem
it? אי כתב רחמנא לא ימכר, ei katav rachmana lo yimacher, if
it just said that, הוה אמינא זבוני הוא דלא מזדבן, hava amina
zivuni hu d'lo mizdaban, selling it you cannot do for מעשר, דקא
עביד ליה כחול, d'ka avid lei k'chol, that's by treating it like,
you know, non-sanctified things, it's what you do with your normal mundane
objects is you sell them. So selling I would have said that
it's limited to selling that I can't do. אבל מיפרק מיפרק, aval
mifrak mifrak, but of course it would have been reasonable to think
that I could redeem my מעשר. You can redeem other קרבנות, korbanot,
why can't you redeem your מעשר? דאיילו דמי להקדש, d'ayilu dmei l'hekdesh,
you're transferring money to be used for a sanctified purpose. להכי כתב
רחמנא לא יגאל, l'hachi katav rachmana lo yiga'el, so it had to
tell me I can't redeem it. If it had not told me
that, I would have not known that it was prohibited. So it
had to tell me don't redeem it. But it told it to
me in a particular context where I should understand that the word
also means don't sell it. דלאו מזדבוני מזדבן, d'lav mizdavuni mizdaban, so
therefore don't sell, ולאו מיפרק מיפרק, v'lav mifrak mifrak, and don't redeem.
But because of the line between alive and dead, we also learn
that sale is only prohibited when it's alive, it's permitted when it's
dead, it's only a rabbinic problem, and therefore we can make exceptions,
and therefore מעשר, not בכור, and therefore we can make exceptions to
selling. So the upshot is בכור can be sold, מעשר cannot, because
לא יגאל means לא ימכר, lo yimacher, but we're saying that prohibition
of selling is limited to when it is alive, not when it
is dead, then it is only rabbinic. And look at that, we
caught up. Okay, יישר כוח. Yasher koach. You all are amazing. יהיה
רצון. יהיה רצון יהיה רצון יהיה רצון Yehi ratzon yehi ratzon yehi
ratzon yehi ratzon. יהיה רצון. Yehi ratzon.